<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ci/cd on Daniel Puig</title>
    <link>/tags/ci/cd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ci/cd on Daniel Puig</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/tags/ci/cd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gitops</title>
      <link>/posts/gitops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 23:21:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/gitops/</guid>
      <description>GitOps is a development and operations methodology that aims to make infrastructure and application deployment as easy and reliable as possible. It does this by using Git as a single source of truth for both infrastructure and application code, as well as for storing and tracking the desired state of the system.
One of the key benefits of GitOps is that it allows for a more collaborative and transparent approach to operations tasks.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;GitOps is a development and operations methodology that aims to make infrastructure and application deployment as easy and reliable as possible. It does this by using Git as a single source of truth for both infrastructure and application code, as well as for storing and tracking the desired state of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key benefits of GitOps is that it allows for a more collaborative and transparent approach to operations tasks. With GitOps, all changes to infrastructure and application code are stored in version control and are subject to review and approval before being deployed. This helps to reduce the risk of errors and makes it easier to rollback changes if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitOps also makes it easier to automate the deployment process. By using tools like GitLab or Jenkins, it is possible to set up a continuous delivery pipeline that automatically deploys code changes when they are pushed to the repository. This can significantly reduce the time it takes to deploy new features and bug fixes, and makes it easier to scale deployments across multiple environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect of GitOps is the emphasis on declarative configuration. Instead of manually provisioning and configuring infrastructure, GitOps practitioners define the desired state of the system using declarative configuration files, such as Kubernetes manifests or Terraform configuration files. These configuration files are then used to automatically provision and configure the necessary infrastructure and applications. This approach makes it easier to understand and manage the system, and makes it easier to replicate the same configuration in different environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, GitOps is a powerful approach to managing infrastructure and applications that can help organizations to deploy more quickly and reliably, while also improving collaboration and transparency. It is particularly well-suited to organizations that are using containerization and cloud-native technologies, and is likely to become increasingly important as these technologies continue to grow in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
